<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 * Ajouter ici d'éventuels commentaires sur le fichier XML
-->
<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" 
          xml:id="lowdisc_sequences" 
          xml:lang="fr"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <pubdate>$LastChangedDate: 16-12-2008 $</pubdate>
  </info>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>sequences</refname>

    <refpurpose>The sequences available in the Low Discrepancy toolbox.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsection>
    <title>Sequences</title>

    <para>
      Several sequences are available in the Low Discrepancy toolbox.
      Each number sequence has its own properties, this is why the goal of
      this page is to detail the properties of these sequences.
      Each sequence can be configured with the -method option.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Classes of sequence</title>
    <para>
      All Low Discrepancy sequences are designed to be able to produce real values uniform in the [0,1[^s interval, where s is the dimension of the space.
    </para>

    <para>
            The generators in this class tries to produces numbers which
            favor the convergence of a Monte-Carlo simulation by reducing the
            discrepancy. These generators may be used, for example, in the
            Monte-Carlo based numerical integration of a function.
          </para>
          <para>
            The list of generators available in this toolbox and producing low discrepancy
            sequences is the following : vandercorput, halton, faure, gslhalton, gslreversehalton,
            gslsobol, gslniederreiter-base-2.
          </para>

  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Sources of Sequences</title>
    <para>
      Although the random number toolbox provides the same interface for all
      generators, what happens behind the scenes is not the same, depending
      on the sequence. Two main sources are used in this toolbox.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Scripts</para>
        <para>
          Scripts are provided with this toolbox to implement both
          low-discrepancy sequences (such as
          Halton for instance).
          These sequences may be slow if a large number of data is to be
          generated, but may provide greater flexibility for some users.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>C++ source codes</para>
        <para>
          These sequences are based on compiled C source code
          and should be as fast as possible.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Overview of sequences</title>
    <para>
      In this section, we detail the sequences which are provided.
    </para>

    <para>
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>"vandercorput"</para>
          <para>
            The Van Der Corput sequence is a low discrepancy sequence.
            It is available only in 1 dimension (i.e. the -dimension option must be set to 1, the default).
            It uses the basis which is associated with the -vandercorputbasis option (default : 2).
            This sequence is based on a script.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>"halton"</para>
          <para>
            The Halton sequence is a low discrepancy sequence.
            It is available for dimensions up to 100 dimensions.
            It uses the list of prime numbers which is associated with the -primeslist option.
            The -primeslist option may be used is the required dimension of the problem is
            larger than the default.
            This sequence is based on a script, which might be slow if a large number of
            data is to be generated. If performance is a problem, the gslhalton sequence
            should be prefered.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>"faure"</para>
          <para>
            The Faure sequence is a low discrepancy sequence.
            It is available for dimensions up to 50 dimensions.
            This sequence is based on a script, which might be slow if a large number of
            data is to be generated.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </refsection>
  <refsection>
    <title>TODO</title>

    <para>
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add missing sequences in this page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </refsection>
  <refsection>
    <title>See Also</title>

    <simplelist type="inline">
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_overview">lowdisc_overview</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_new">lowdisc_new</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_cget">lowdisc_cget</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_configure">lowdisc_configure</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_display">lowdisc_display</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_next">lowdisc_next</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_terms">lowdisc_terms</link>
      </member>
      <member>
        <link linkend="lowdisc_destroy">lowdisc_destroy</link>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </refsection>

</refentry>
