<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 * Copyright (C) 2013 - Michael Baudin
 * Copyright (C) 2010 - 2011 - DIGITEO - Michael Baudin
 * This file is released under the terms of the GNU LGPL license.
-->
<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="lowdisc_overview" xml:lang="fr"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Overview</refname>

    <refpurpose>An overview of the Low Discrepancy toolbox.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsection>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>
      The goal of this toolbox is to provide a collection of low
      discrepancy sequences. These sequences try to produce numbers which favor
      the convergence of a Monte-Carlo simulation by reducing the discrepancy.
      These random numbers are designed to be used in a
      Monte-Carlo simulation. For example, low discrepancy sequences provide a
      higher convergence rate to the Monte-Carlo method when used in numerical
      integration. The toolbox takes into account the dimension of the problem,
      i.e. generate vectors with arbitrary size.
    </para>

    <para>
      Low Discrepancy sequences are designed to be able to produce
      real values uniform in the [0,1[^s interval, where s is the dimension of
      the space.
    </para>

    <para>
      See the provided demonstrations for sample examples of this library.
    </para>

  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Overview of sequences</title>

    <para>
      The list of sequences which are provided in this component is the following.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Halton sequence.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The leaped Halton sequence.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The scrambled Halton sequence of Kocis and Whiten 
		  ("Reverse Radix" or "RR2").</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Reverse Halton sequence of Vandewoestyne and Cools.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Faure sequence.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Sobol sequence. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The scrambled Sobol sequence : Owen, Faure-Tezuka or 
		  Owen-Faure-Tezuka scramblings. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Niederreiter base 2 and arbitrary base sequence. </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Features</title>

    <para>
      The current component has the following features : <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>manage arbitrary number of dimensions,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>skips a given number of elements in the sequence,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            leaps (i.e. ignores) a given number of elements from call to
            call,
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fast sequences based on compiled source code,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>suggest optimal settings to make the best use of the sequences,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>object oriented programming, if necessary.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Quick Start</title>

    <para>
      The following example generates 20 points from a Sobol 
	  sequence in dimension 4.
      This is a simplified use of the library, where we know in advance the number
      of experiments to perform.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="example">
      <![CDATA[
u=lowdisc_ldgen(20,4)
   ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      Assume now that we want to use a scrambled Halton sequence. 
	  The following calling sequence creates a 
	  scrambled Halton sequence with 20 points in 4 dimensions. 
	  This may potentially reduce the correlations 
	  which may appear in high dimensions.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="example">
      <![CDATA[
u=lowdisc_ldgen(20,4,"halton-scrambled")
   ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
	  It may happen that we have to generate the points block-by-block, 
	  instead of all-at-once. 
	  In this case, we may use the following functions. 
      The following example creates 1000 points in dimension 4 from the Sobol sequence.
      This way of using the library allows to get a complete control over the
      parameters of the sequence.
      It also allows to generate the points one by one, which may be
      useful to save memory.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="example">
      <![CDATA[
rng = lowdisc_new("sobol");
rng = lowdisc_configure(rng,"-dimension",4);
rng = lowdisc_startup (rng);
// Get first point
[rng,computed]=lowdisc_next(rng);
// Get second point
[rng,computed]=lowdisc_next(rng);
// Get 1000 points
[rng,computed]=lowdisc_next(rng,1000);
rng = lowdisc_destroy(rng);
   ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      The function lowdisc_methods returns the list of available
      sequences. 
      The following script displays the available sequences
      and a table displaying the speed, maximum dimension and
      maximum number of calls for all sequences.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="example">
      <![CDATA[
// Get all the available sequences.
seqmat = lowdisc_methods ();
// Get the speed, maximum dimension and
// maximum number of calls for all sequences
seqmat = lowdisc_methods ();
mprintf("%-20s %-10s %-10s\n", "Name" , ..
"Max Dim" , "Max Call" );
for seqname = seqmat'
    lds = lowdisc_new(seqname);
    dimmax = lowdisc_get(lds,"-dimmax");
    nbsimmax = lowdisc_get(lds,"-nbsimmax");
    mprintf("%-20s %-10d %-10d\n", seqname , ..
    dimmax , nbsimmax );
    lds = lowdisc_destroy(lds);
end
   ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      The previous script produces the following output.
      When the maximum number of calls is equal to -1, this means
      that there is, in principle, no limit in the number of
      elements which can be generated.
    </para>

    <screen>
      Name                Max Dim    Max Call
      halton              100        2147483647
      faure               541        2147483647
      sobol               1111       1073741823
      niederreiter        50         2147483647
    </screen>

  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Design</title>

    <para>
      The main components in this toolbox are the following.

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>lowdisc_ldgen</literal> function
            can produce a complete set of points, given the name of a sequence and
            the number of dimension.
            Moreover, this function makes use of optimized <literal>skip</literal>
            and <literal>leap</literal> parameters,
            which may reduce the discrepancy of the sequence.
            Moreover, the number of generated points can be optimized to reduce
            the discrepancy.
            This is the flagship of this toolbox.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sequences:
          </para>
          <para>
            The <literal>lowdisc_*</literal> functions provide the highest level object oriented
            functions.
            They allow to access to any sequence with a constructor based
            on a string representing the sequence. For example, 
            <literal>lds = lowdisc_new("halton")</literal>
            creates a new Halton sequence.
            In this framework, the lowdisc component allows to access to all sequences
            with a single API, where all the methods are valid for all sequences and
            all sequences share the same options.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Static Functions:
          </para>
          <para>
            These functions are macros which provides parameters which can
            be used in low discrepancy sequences such as <literal>skip</literal>
            and <literal>leap</literal> parameters, or tables of prime numbers.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>The zero</title>

    <para>
      The zero vector is never produced by the low discrepancy 
	  generators in this toolbox. 
	  This allows to avoid problem when inverting a cumulated 
	  distribution function, because the zero probability may 
	  be associated with an infinite outcome (e.g. for the 
	  multivariate normale distribution). 
    </para>

    <para>
      However, in order to graphically show the low discrepancy properties 
	  of some sequences, it may be useful to include the zero. 
	  For example, the following code compute the first 100 points of the 
	  Halton sequence in s=5 dimensions. 
	  Then we use the <literal>zeros</literal> function in order 
	  to insert the zero row vector at the start of the sequence.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="example">
      <![CDATA[
s=5;
u=lowdisc_ldgen(10,s, "halton" );
u = [zeros(1,s);u]
   ]]>
    </programlisting>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Authors</title>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>2012-2013 - Michael Baudin</member>
      <member>2009-2011 - DIGITEO - Michael Baudin</member>
      <member>2008-2009 - INRIA - Michael Baudin</member>
      <member>2003-2009 - John Burkardt</member>
      <member>1994 - Paul Bratley, Bennett Fox, Harald Niederreiter</member>
      <member>1986-1988 - Bennett Fox</member>
    </simplelist>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>
      Michael Baudin thanks John Burkardt for his help during
      the development of this library.
    </para>
    <para>
      Thanks to Alan Cornet, Pierre Marechal for the technical help
      for this project.
    </para>
    <para>
      Thanks to Jean-Philippe Chancelier for finding bugs in the
      source code of the gateway.
    </para>

  </refsection>


  <refsection>
    <title>Licence</title>

    <para>
      This toolbox is distributed under the GNU LGPL license.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection>
    <title>Bibliography</title>

    <para>
      "Monte-Carlo methods in Financial Engineering", Paul Glasserman,
      Springer, 2003
    </para>

    <para>
      "Algorithm 247: Radical-inverse quasi-random point sequence", J. H.
      Halton, 1964. Commun. ACM 7, 12 (Dec. 1964), 701-702
    </para>

    <para>
      "Good permutations for deterministic scrambled Halton sequences in
      terms of L2-discrepancy", B. Vandewoestyne and R. Cools, Computational and
      Applied Mathematics 189, 2006
    </para>

    <para>
      "Low-discrepancy and low-dispersion sequences", Harald Niederreiter,
      Journal of Number Theory, Volume 30, 1988, pages 51-70.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Algorithm 647: Implementation and Relative Efficiency of
      Quasirandom Sequence Generators", B. L. Fox, 1986. ACM Trans. Math. Softw.
      12, 4 (Dec. 1986), 362-376.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Algorithm 659: Implementing Sobol's quasirandom sequence
      generator.", P. Bratley and B. L. Fox, 1988. ACM Trans. Math. Softw. 14, 1
      (Mar. 1988), 88-100.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Remark on Algorithm 659: Implementing Sobol's Quasirandom Sequence
      Generator", Stephen Joe, Frances Kuo, ACM Transactions on Mathematical
      Software, Volume 29, Number 1, March 2003, pages 49-57.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Implementation and Tests of Low Discrepancy Sequences",
      Paul Bratley, Bennett Fox, Harald Niederreiter,
      ACM Transactions on Modeling and Computer Simulation,
      Volume 2, Number 3, July 1992, pages 195-213.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Algorithm 738: Programs to generate Niederreiter's low-discrepancy
      sequences", P. Bratley, B. L. Fox, and H. Niederreiter, 1994. ACM Trans.
      Math. Softw. 20, 4 (Dec. 1994), 494-495.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Algorithm 823: Implementing scrambled digital sequences", H. S.
      Hong and F. J. Hickernell, 2003. ACM Trans. Math. Softw. 29, 2 (Jun.
      2003), 95-109.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Discrepancy of sequences associated with a number system (in
      dimension one)", Faure Henri, Bull. Soc. Math. France 109, no. 2,
      143--182, 1981
    </para>

    <para>
      "Numerical Recipes in Fortran: The Art of Scientific Computing",
      William Press, Brian Flannery, Saul Teukolsky, William Vetterling, Second
      Edition, Cambridge University Press, 1992
    </para>

    <para>
      "Comparison of Point Sets and Sequences for Quasi-Monte Carlo and
      for Random Number Generation.", L'Ecuyer, P. 2008. In Proceedings of the
      5th international Conference on Sequences and their Applications
      (Lexington, KY, USA, September 14 - 18, 2008). S. W. Golomb, M. G. Parker,
      A. Pott, and A. Winterhof, Eds. Lecture Notes In Computer Science, vol.
      5203. Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Heidelberg, 1-17.
    </para>

    <para>
      "Computational investigations of low-discrepancy sequences", Kocis,
      L. and Whiten, W. J. 1997. ACM Trans. Math. Softw. 23, 2 (Jun. 1997),
      266-294.
    </para>

    <para>"Gnu Scientific Library - The Reverse Halton Sequence", Olivier Teytaud, 2007</para>

    <para>"USSR Computational Mathematics and Mathematical Physics", Ilya Sobol, Volume 16, pages 236-242, 1977.</para>

    <para>"The Production of Points Uniformly Distributed in a Multidimensional Cube" (in Russian), Ilya Sobol, YL Levitan, Preprint IPM Akad. Nauk SSSR, Number 40, Moscow 1976.</para>

    <para>
	"Random Number Generation and Quasi-Monte Carlo Methods", 
	Harald Niederreiter, SIAM, 1992.
	</para>

  </refsection>
</refentry>

