<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
 * 
 * This help file was generated from lowdisc_configure.sci using help_from_sci().
 * 
 -->

<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="lowdisc_configure" xml:lang="en"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <info>
    <pubdate>$LastChangedDate: 26-Avr-2010 $</pubdate>
  </info>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>lowdisc_configure</refname><refpurpose>Configure a field of the object and returns the modified object.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>



<refsynopsisdiv>
   <title>Calling Sequence</title>
   <synopsis>
   this = lowdisc_configure (this,key,value)
   
   </synopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
   <title>Parameters</title>
   <variablelist>
   <varlistentry><term>this:</term>
      <listitem><para> the current object</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>key:</term>
      <listitem><para> a string. The name of the option to get. All options which can be set with lowdisc_configure can be get with lowdisc_cget.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>value:</term>
      <listitem><para> the value associated with the key. Its type depends on the value of the key.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Description</title>
   <para>
This command allows to configure the state of the current object.
It requires to take the current object both as an input
and output argument.
The following keys are available.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>"-verbose" : a boolean, the verbose mode (default : %f).</listitem>
<listitem>"-dimension" : a positive floating point integer,
the dimension of the space, i.e.
the size of the vector returned by the command lowdisc_next (default = 1).</listitem>
<listitem>"-method" : a string, the low discrepancy sequence (default = "halton").</listitem>
<listitem>"-vandercorputbasis" : a positive floating point integer, greater or equal to 2,
the basis used in the Van Der Corput sequence (default = 2).
The value is expected to be . It should be a prime number, but that
is not checked by the configure method.</listitem>
<listitem>"-primeslist" : a row array of positive floating point integers,
at matrix of prime numbers used in the several low discrepancy sequences.
The expected matrix must have a 1xn shape, with n an integer greater than 2.
The default list is made of the 100 first prime numbers, from 2 to 541, which
enables the user to generate sequences up to 100 dimensions.
If a larger dimension problem is to process, that feature should enable users to
customize the list to meet the required dimension.
The user should be warned that the Halton sequence may produce poor convergence
rate if the dimension is larger than 15.</listitem>
<listitem>"-sequenceindex" : a positive floating point integer,
the starting index of the low discrepancy sequences.
When a sequence is created this setting is initialized to 0.
Whenever the randonumber_next method is called, the sequence index
is updated and incremented with 1. If this option is passed to the lowdisc_cget
method, it allows to know the number of vectors which have allready
been generated.
If this option is set, it allows to modify the behaviour of the low discrepancy
sequences, which take into account this index to produce the next element
in the sequence.
The -sequenceindex optin should therefore generally not be set,
except in specific situations
where the user has particular requirements on the low discrepancy
sequence to generate.</listitem>
<listitem>"-skip" : a positive floating point integer,
the number of terms to skip at startup.
When the sequence is started up with the lowdisc_startup method,
the algorithm generates skip elements, which are immediately
discarded. This option allows to start the simulation at a later
point in the sequence.
For example, Fox recommends to skip the qs^4 - 2 first terms in the
Faure sequence, where qs is the prime number associated with the
sequence. This number can be retrieved with
qs = lowdisc_get ( rng , "-faureprime" ).</listitem>
<listitem>"-leap" : a positive floating point integer,
the number of elements to ignore from element to element (default = 0).
Each time the lowdisc_next function is called, the immediate element
is retrieved. Then, in order to prepare for the next call,
there are leap elements which are generated and immediately
discarded. This option allows to generate alternative
sequences based on the same basic generator.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
The following is the list of possible values for "-method".
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>"vandercorput" : the Van Der Corput low
discrepancy sequence.
It is available only in 1 dimension (i.e. the -dimension option must be
set to 1, the default). It uses the basis which is associated with
the "-vandercorputbasis" option.
This is a macro-based algorithm.</listitem>
<listitem>"halton" : the Halton low discrepancy sequence.
This sequence is sensitive to the "-primeslist" option.
This is a macro-based algorithm.</listitem>
<listitem>"faure" : the Faure low discrepancy sequence.
This sequence is sensitive to the "-primeslist" option.
This is a macro-based algorithm.</listitem>
<listitem>"reversehalton" : the Reverse Halton sequence of Vandewoestyne and Cools.
This sequence is sensitive to the "-primeslist" option.
This is a macro-based algorithm. </listitem>
<listitem>"sobol" : the Sobol sequence.
This sequence is available for problems where the dimension is lower than 40.
This is a macro-based algorithm.
The current implementation is a Scilab port of the source code in Matlab
by John Burkardt. The original source code was created by Bennett Fox in Fortran.
</listitem>
<listitem>"niederreiter-base-2" : The Niederreiter Base 2 sequence.
This is a macro-based algorithm.
The implementation is a Scilab port of the Matlab source code by John Burkardt.
Original Fortran 77 version by Paul Bratley, Bennett Fox, Harald Niederreiter.
</listitem>
<listitem>"reversehaltonf" : the Reverse Halton sequence of Vandewoestyne and Cools.
This fast algorithm is based on a compiled C source code. </listitem>
<listitem>"niederreiter-base-2f" : The Niederreiter Base 2 sequence.
This fast algorithm is based on a compiled C source code. </listitem>
<listitem>"sobolf" : the Sobol sequence.
This fast algorithm is based on a compiled C source code. </listitem>
<listitem>"fauref" : the Faure sequence.
This fast algorithm is based on a compiled C source code. </listitem>
<listitem>"haltonf" : the Halton sequence.
This fast algorithm is based on a compiled C source code. </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Examples</title>
   <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
rng = lowdisc_new();
rng = lowdisc_configure(rng,"-method","faure");
rng = lowdisc_configure(rng,"-dimension",3);
method = lowdisc_cget(rng,"-method")
nbdim = lowdisc_cget(rng,"-dimension")
i = lowdisc_cget(rng,"-sequenceindex")
verbose = lowdisc_cget(rng,"-verbose")
rng
rng = lowdisc_destroy(rng);

   ]]></programlisting>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Authors</title>
   <simplelist type="vert">
   <member>Michael Baudin - 2008-2009 - INRIA</member>
   <member>Michael Baudin - 2010 - DIGITEO</member>
   </simplelist>
</refsection>
</refentry>
